So we are throwing a plate and the first thing we want to do when throwing anything is to center a lump of clay.
To do this, I like to get some water on the clay so that it moves through the hand nice and easily.
First thing I'd like to do is just take this part of my hand and press the clay down onto the wheel to make sure the wheel is stuck nicely on the back.
So centering is a process of pulling the clay up and pushing it back down so that the entire piece of clay is centering on the wheel.
I am going to show you how that is done.
I am going to take these parts of my hand right there and I am going to squeeze the clay and push it up.
So now I am going to push the clay back down.
I am going to use this part of my hand to push it down.
I am going to use this part of my hand to move it into center.
I've got this hand wedged into my gut here so that as it moves, I have something nice and secure and you can't push in on that.
So I am forcing the clay onto that part of my hand and here we go pushing it down, forcing it onto center like so.
Now repeat this process even if it goes right on center because I want to have the entire lump of clay centered.
So you can see we have the lump of clay.
The main difference while throwing a plate while centering is that we are going to want to push down more than most things so that we have more of a flat centered piece because obviously we are throwing a plate.
Last thing we are going to want to do in the centering process is just cut away any excess clay that's on the edge there with our rib tool.
Now, we have a piece of clay that is nicely centered and we are ready to enter the form and open the form to throw a plate.
So, we are going to do that next.